The Oral History Program
The Museum of Modern Art, Publisher
The Oral History Program
1987-
The Museum of Modern Art, Museum Archives 11 West 53 Street New York, NY 10019-5497 moma.org/learn/resources/archives
Museum of Modern Art (New York, N.Y.). Museum Archives
Oral history interviews conducted with individuals related to The Museum of Modern Art
Scope and Content
The purpose of the Oral History Program is to fill gaps in the written record on specific topics. Oral histories serve to enhance and complement the Museum Archives' holdings of documentary material with first-hand observation, recollections and reflections. Importantly, our Oral History Program is MoMA-centric. Increasingly, interviews with artists are being undertaken to discuss the role of the Museum in the life of the artist, as well as to interview the artist about works of art in the Museum Collection and to discuss the artist's process, use of materials, and the larger context within which a particular work of art was made.
Arrangement
Series I: Artists
Series II: Trustees and Donors
Series III: Administrative and Curatorial Staff
Series IV: Museum Building and Expansion
Series V: MoMA PS1
Series VI: Art World
Series VII: Exhibition Documentaries
Series VIII: Restricted Interviews
Related Material
Other collections containing recorded interviews in The Museum of Modern Art Archives are the Sound Recordings of Museum-Related Events collection, the Video Recordings of Museum-Related Events collection, the David Hoffman MoMA History Interviews, and the Calvin Tomkins Papers.
Restrictions on Access
Transcripts of the oral history interviews are accessible for use in the Archives' reading room in Manhattan. Audio recordings of the interviews are restricted and not available. Digital video footage of artists who were interviewed as part of the Museum's 2011-2012 Artist Oral History Initiative is available for use in the Archives' reading room in Manhattan. The Museum Archives seeks to make the oral history interviews acessible to researchers to the fullest extent possible in accordance with signed agreements with the participants and established access policies. Please note that some oral histories have been conducted but have not at this time been cleared for public use and are listed in Series VII: Restricted Interviews.
Container List
- Series I: Artists
  Participants within this series are artists represented in the Museum's collection and/or have a relationship with the Museum. In some instances, these interviews contain focused dialogue about specific works in the collection. In addition, some artists are former Museum staff.
  - Vito Acconci, 2011; Interview part of 2011-2012 Artist Oral History Initiative Video Project
  - Vija Celmins, 2011; Interview part of 2011-2012 Artist Oral History Initiative Video Project
  - Chuck Close, 1996
  - Dan Graham, 2011; Interview part of 2011-2012 Artist Oral History Initiative Video Project
  - Jasper Johns, 1994
  - Jeff Koons, 1999
  - Sol LeWitt, 1994
  - Robert Mangold, 1999
  - Allan McCollum, 1999
  - Bruce Nauman, 2011; Interview part of 2011-2012 Artist Oral History Initiative Video Project
  - Yvonne Rainer, 2011; Interview part of 2011-2012 Artist Oral History Initiative Video Project
  - Robert Rauschenberg, 2006
  - Ed Ruscha, 2011; Interview part of 2011-2012 Artist Oral History Initiative Video Project
  - James Turrell, 2010; Interview part of the 2010 MoMA PS1 Oral History Initiative
- Series II: Trustees and Donors
  Participants within this series are Museum Trustees and donors. Topics covered may include the Museum's Board, participation on committees, acquisitions, donations and their overall experience with the Museum at various points in its history.
  - Lily Auchincloss, 1993
  - Walter Bareiss, 1991
  - Celeste G. Bartos, 1993
  - Elizabeth Bliss Parkinson Cobb, 1988
  - Elaine Dannheisser, 1996
  - Mrs. Agustn E. (Mal) Edwards, 1998
  - Duke Franz of Bavaria, 1998
  - Barbara Jakobson, 1997
  - Philip Johnson, 1990, 1991, 1995
  - June Larkin, 2004
  - Margaret McDermott, 1998
  - John Rewald, 1991
  - Mrs. Bertram (Louise Reinhardt) Smith, 1992
  - Joanne Stern, 1993
  - Mrs. Donald B. (Beth) Straus, 1993
  - Jeanne C. Thayer, 1994
  - Edward M.M. Warburg, 1991
  - Richard Zeisler, 1998
- Series III: Administrative and Curatorial Staff
  Participants within this series are former Museum staff members reflecting upon their professional experience at the Museum. Topics include, but are not limited to, exhibition history, acquisitions, the Museum's expansion projects, recollections of artists and other staff, and descriptions of various Museum programs.
  - Emilio Ambasz, 1993, 1994
  - Franoise Boas, 1991
  - Eileen Bowser, 2000
  - Olive Bragazzi, 1998
  - William Burback, 1999
  - Riva Castleman, 1995, 1996
  - Miriam Goldman Cedarbaum, 2000
  - Mildred Constantine, 1991
  - Helen M. Franc, 1991
  - Wilder Green, 1991
  - John B. Hightower, 1996
  - Philip Johnson, 1990, 1991, 1995
  - Betsy B. Jones, 1994
  - Victor Jules-Louis, 1998
  - Antoinette King, 1997
  - Richard H. Koch, 1991
  - Luisa Kreisberg, 2003
  - Sandra Lang Landsman, 1999
  - Alicia Legg, 1991
  - William S. Lieberman, 1993
  - Grace M. Mayer, 1991
  - Sara Mazo, 1993
  - Porter McCray, 1991, 1993
  - Pearl L. Moeller, 1991
  - Richard E. Oldenburg, 1999
  - Richard Palmer, 2003
  - Frances Pernas, 1994
  - Waldo Rasmussen, 1994
  - Eloise Ricciardelli, 1994
  - Gilbert S. Robinson, 2002
  - William S. Rubin, 1993, 1994
  - Peter Selz, 1994
  - Elizabeth Shaw, 1991
  - Robert Storr, 2004
  - Ione Ulrich Sutton, 1993
  - John Szarkowski, 1993
  - Richard Tooke, 1998
  - Kirk Varnedoe, 2001, 2002
  - Jean Volkmer, 1991
  - Monroe Wheeler, 1987
  - Stuart Wrede, 1997; Advance permission from Stuart Wrede required to access interview
- Series IV: Art World
  Participants within this series are art dealers, historians, and collectors who have had a relationship with the Museum. Conversation topics typically cover research for books authored, works acquired by the Museum, MoMA exhibitions, and relationships with artists whom the Museum has represented in its collection.
  - Irving Blum, 2011
  - Leo Castelli, 1991, 1992
  - S. Lane Faison, 2001
  - Grace Glueck, 1997
  - Anne d'Harnoncourt, 2003, 2004
  - Ben Heller, 2001
  - Sidney Janis, 1967
  - Dorothy Lichtenstein, 1998
  - Lucy Lippard, 1999
  - Ileana Sonnabend, 1997
- Series V: Museum Building and Expansion
  Participants within this series are architects, developers and lawyers involved in the Museum's major 1984 expansion campaign designed by architect Cesar Pelli. Other topics may include the Trust for Cultural Resources, the Museum's Sculpture Garden, fundraising, and zoning legislation.
  - Donald H. Elliott, 1994
  - Philip Johnson, 1990, 1991, 1995
  - Richard Koch, 1991
  - Cesar Pelli, 1994
  - Richard Weinstein, 1991
- Series VI: MoMA PS1
  Participants within this series have an important connection to MoMA PS1 Contemporary Art Center. In 2000, MoMA became affiliated with PS1, and the two institutions fully merged in 2010, thus extending the reach of both institutions. Topics in this series may include MoMA PS1's founding, commissioned artwork, MoMA PS1's studio program, exhibition history, fundraising, and its merger with MoMA.
  - John Comfort, 2011
  - Tom Finkelpearl, 2010
  - James Turrell, 2010
- Series VII: Exhibition Documentaries
  From 2003 to 2009, the Museum undertook a series of oral history-inspired interviews related to special MoMA exhibitions. These exhibition documentaries featured curators and artists discussing the exhibition in situ. The series of exhibition documentaries was initiated in 2003 under the guidance of Mary Lea Bandy, Deputy Director of Curatorial Affairs, and CK Studios produced the videos. DVD copies of the interviews are available in the MoMA Archives, and the HDCam masters are held by the Museum's Department of Film.
  - Matisse Picasso[MoMA Exh. #1906, February 13, 2003 - May 19, 2003], Participants include Chief Curator at Large John Elderfield and Department of Painting and Sculpture Chief Curator Kirk Varnedoe.; See also Video Recordings of Museum-Related Events, 2008-213.
  - Friedlander[MoMA Exh. #1943, June 5, 2005-August 29, 2005], 2003; Participants include artist Lee Friedlander and Department of Photography Chief Curator Peter Galassi.; See also Video Recordings of Museum-Related Events, 2008-46.
  - Pioneering Modern Painting: Cézanne and Pissarro 1865-1885[MoMA Exh. #1944, June 26, 2005-September 12, 2005], Participants include Department of Painting and Sculpture Curator Joachim Pissarro and Chief Curator John Elderfield.; See also Video Recordings of Museum-Related Events, 2008-47.
  - Elizabeth Murray[MoMA Exh. #1955, October 28, 2005-January 9, 2006], Participants include artist Elizabeth Murray and Department of Painting and Sculpture Curator Robert Storr.; See also Video Recordings of Museum-Related Events, 2008-48 and 2008-48D.
  - Richard Serra Sculpture: Forty Years[MoMA Exh. #2007, June 3, 2007-September 24, 2007], Participants include artist Richard Serra and Dia Foundation Curator Lynne Cooke.; See also Video Recordings of Museum-Related Events, 2008-49.
- Series VIII: Restricted Interviews
  Interviews within this series are unavailable for public access at this time.
  - Artists
    - Richard Hamilton, 2009
    - Ellsworth Kelly, 1991, 1999, 2012; 2012 interview part of 2011-2012 Artist Oral History Initiative Video Project
    - Jim Rosenquist, 2012; Interview part of 2011-2012 Artist Oral History Initiative Video Project
    - Robert Ryman, 1993
    - Yoko Ono, 2011; Interview part of 2011-2012 Artist Oral History Initiative Project Transcript of audio recording only
  - Trustees and Donors
    - Agnes Gund, 2009,2012
    - Donald B. Marron, 1994, 1996
    - David Rockefeller, 1991, 2001
  - Administrative and Curatorial Staff
    - Carolyn Lanchner, 2003
    - Deborah Wye, 2011
    - Kynaston McShine, 2010, 2011
    - Bernice Rose, 2002
  - Art World
    - Paula Cooper, 1996
  - Exhibition Documentaries
    - Martin Puryear[MoMA Exh. #2021. November 4, 2007-January 14, 2008], Participants include artist Martin Puryear and Chief Curator of Painting and Sculpture John Elderfield.; See also Video Recordings of Museum-Related Events, 2010-18 and 2010-18D.